Paul Field Sifton and Claire Sifton Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Paul Field Sifton and Claire Sifton Papers 1912-1980 1925-1971
MSS48074
Sifton, Paul Field, 1897-1972
Sifton, Claire, 1897-1980
25,500 items
78 containers plus 2 oversize
32.3 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Paul Field Sifton, playwright, government official, and Claire Sifton, editor and author. Correspondence, diaries, writings, subject files, family papers, printed matter, and miscellany relating to the Siftons' literary, labor, and governmental careers.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Adams, Esther Root, 1872 or 1873-1960--Correspondence.; Atkinson, Brooks, 1894-1984--Correspondence.; Douglas, Helen Gahagan, 1900-1980--Correspondence.; Douglas, Paul H. (Paul Howard), 1892-1976--Correspondence.; Ford, Henry, 1863-1947.; Frank, Walter, 1905-1945--Correspondence.; Howe, Ruth Esther--Correspondence.; Kennedy, John F. (John Fitzgerald), 1917-1963--Correspondence.; Kranz, Heinrich (German translator)--Correspondence.; Loeb, James I. (James Isaac), 1908- --Correspondence.; Loth, David, 1899-1988--Correspondence.; Millay, Norma--Correspondence.; Morrison, Adrienne, 1883-1940--Correspondence.; Niebuhr, Reinhold, 1892-1971--Correspondence.; Patton, James G. (James George), 1902- --Correspondence.; Portes, Hélène, comtesse de, 1902-1940.; Reuther, Roy, 1909-1968--Correspondence.; Reuther, Victor G. (Victor George), 1912- --Correspondence.; Reuther, Walter, 1907-1970--Correspondence.; Reynaud, Paul, 1878-1966.; Rose, Carl, 1902?-1971--Correspondence.; Salisbury, Leah Javne, 1893-1975--Correspondence.; Shumlin, Herman, 1898-1979--Correspondence.; Sifton, Claire, 1897-1980. Paul Field Sifton and Claire Sifton papers. 1912-1980.; Sifton, Paul Field, 1897-1972.; Swope, Herbert Bayard, 1882-1958--Correspondence.
Organizations
International Union, United Automobile Workers of America (CIO); National Council for a Permanent Fair Employment Practice Committee.; National Farmers' Union (U.S.); Union for Democratic Action.; United States. Department of the Interior.; United States. War Manpower Commission.
Subjects
Agriculture and state--United States.; American drama--20th century.; Assembly-line methods.; Capital punishment.; Civil rights--United States.; Depressions--1929--United States.; Energy policy.; Full employment policies--United States.; Labor laws and legislation--United States.; Labor movement--Political aspects--United States.; Labor movement--United States.; Labor unions--Political activity--United States.; Labor unions--United States.; Literature.; Lobbying--United States.; Medical ethics.; Nazis--Germany.; New Deal, 1933-1939.; Nutrition policy.; Political participation--United States.; Pollution.; Power resources.; Proteins in human nutrition.; Reformers--United States.; Renewable energy sources.; Sensationalism in journalism.; Social movements--Political aspects--United States.; Social problems--Drama.; Theater and society.; Theater--United States.; Unemployment--United States.; Women college students--United States.; Women employees--New York (State)--New York.; World War, 1939-1945--France.
Places
Manhattan (New York, N.Y.)--Social life and customs.; United States--Politics and government--20th century.; United States--Social conditions--20th century.; United States--Social policy--20th century.; Washington (D.C.)--Social life and customs.
Titles
Claire Sifton papers; Paul Field Sifton papers
Occupations
Authors.; Dramatists.; Editors.; Public officials.
Acquisition Information
The papers of Paul Field Sifton, playwright, government official, and lobbyist, and Claire Sifton, editor and author, were given to the Library of Congress in 1941, 1966-1967, and 1972, by Claire Sifton. Additions were given by their son, Paul Ginsburg Sifton, 1982-1987.
Transfers
Sound recordings have been transferred to the Library's Motion Picture, Broadcasting, and Recorded Sound Division where they are identified as part of these papers.
Other Repositories
Additional office files and documentation on Paul Sifton's UAW service are located in the UAW-CIO Papers, Labor History Collection, Wayne State University, Detroit, Mich. Paul Sifton is also represented in the Helen Gahagan Douglas and Melvyn Douglas Papers in the University of Oklahoma Library, Norman, Okla., and in the Paul H. Douglas Papers in the Chicago Historical Society, Chicago, Ill.
Related Material
Other collections in the Manuscript Division containing correspondence or material of Paul Sifton include the National Urban League Records, the National Association for the Advancement of Colored People Records, the Robert Houghwout Jackson Papers, the Harold L. Ickes Papers, the Irving Brant papers, and the Work Projects Administration /Federal Writers' Project file on New York City (Panorama file on industry and commerce), wherein Paul Sifton reviewed a section on unemployment insurance. A file of the professional correspondence of Claire Sifton is located in the records of the National Consumers' League and the records of the Women's Joint Congressional Committee.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Paul Field Sifton and Claire Sifton are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Biographical Note
Paul Field Sifton
Date Event
1897, Oct. 17 Born, Rockford, Ill.
1915 Graduate, Benton Harbor, Mich., high school
1917 1919 Private, first class, Headquarters Company, 6th Field Artillery, 1st Division, American Expeditionary Forces, invalided out with diagnosis of pulmonary tuberculosis
1919 1920 Attended University of Missouri, Columbia, Mo., on federal program for disabled veterans
1921 Attended London School of Economics, London, England
1922 Married Claire E. Ginsburg
1922 1923 Reporter, Des Moines Register, Staten Island Advance, United Press syndicate, Chicago Journal, and the New Leader
1923 1931 Assistant Sunday editor, feature writer, and reporter, New York World
1927 Play, The Belt, produced by the New Playwrights' Theatre, published by Macaulay, New York
1929 Veterans Administration ruled tuberculosis that his was arrested; awarded reduced disability pension
1930 Play written with Claire Sifton, Midnight, produced by the Theatre Guild; Universal motion picture (1934); and West German television play (1957)
1931 Play written with Claire Sifton, 1931---, produced by the Group Theatre and the Theatre Guild; published by Farrar & Rinehart, New York; and produced in London as The Age of Plenty (1933)
1933 Play written with Claire Sifton, Blood on the Moon, produced at the Mayan Theatre, Los Angeles, Calif; the London, England, production was halted by the Lord Chamberlain as an unfriendly act to a foreign country, Germany
1933 1934 On editorial staff, New Yorker
1934 1938 Labor publications editor, assistant industrial commissioner, deputy industrial commissioner and administrator, and executive director, Division of Placement and Unemployment Insurance, New York State Department of Labor
1938 One-act play written with Claire Sifton, Give All Thy Terrors to the Wind, published in the New Theatre an Film Magazine (January 1938), and in the anthology, Best Short Plays of the Social Theatre, edited by William Kozlenko (New York, Random House, 1938) One-act play written with Claire Sifton, Kate Larsen, published in the One Act Play Magazine (June-July 1938 issue)
1938 1939 Deputy administrator, Wages and Hours Division, U.S. Department of Labor
1939 One-act play written with Claire Ginsburg Sifton, The Doctors, produced in Boston, Mass., and Baltimore, Md.
1939 1941 Consumers' counsel, Bituminous Coal Administration, U.S. Department of the Interior
1942 1945 Labor and public relations director, National Farmers' Union, Washington, D.C., office
1944 1945 Director, Washington D. C., office, Union for Democratic Action [later Americans for Democratic Action], and editor with Claire Sifton of the U.D.A. Congressional Newsletter
1945 1947 Worked on legislative and public relations for various causes, including Full Employment Bill (1945), protection of the Children's Bureau under Reorganization Bill No. 2 (1946), Labor Extension Service bill, National Council for a permanent Fair Employment Practices bill), National Consumers' League, and others
1948 1962 National legislative representative, United Automobile Workers [later part of the Congress of Industrial Organizations]
1963 Diagnosed as having chronic bronchitis; Veterans Administration awarded higher disability pension; emphysema and bronchiectasis claims disallowed as not service-connected
1972, Apr. 4 Died, Oaxaca, Mexico
Claire Sifton
Date Event
1897, Dec. 23 Born, Campos, Rio de Janiero State, Brazil
1911 1914 Attended Greenville, S.C., Female Seminary, and Hyde Park School, Kansas City, Mo.
1915 1918 Attended Stephens College, Columbia, Mo.
1920 B.A. in journalism, University of Missouri, Columbia, Mo.
1920 1922 Worked in Chicago, Ill., as feature writer for Montgomery Ward and Co., and the Saturday Blade
1922 Married Paul Field Sifton
1923 31 Worked as feature writer and freelance journalist for the Public Ledger, the Fifth Avenue Coach Co., and the New York Evening World syndicate, and others
1929 Published under the name of Claire Morton The Perfect Baby. New York: Vanguard Press
1930 Play written with Paul Field Sifton, Midnight, produced by the Theatre Guild; Universal motion picture (1934); and West German television play (1957)
1931 Play written with Paul Field Sifton, 1931---, produced by the Group Theatre and the Theatre Guild; published by Farrar & Rinehart, New York; and produced in London as The Age of Plenty (1933)
1933 Play written with Paul Field Sifton, Blood on the Moon, produced at the Mayan Theatre, Los Angeles, Calif.; London, England, production was halted by Lord Chamberlain as an unfriendly act to a foreign country, Germany
1938 One-act play written with Paul Field Sifton, Give All Thy Terrors to the Wind, published in the New Theatre and Film Magazine (January 1938), and in the anthology, Best Short Plays of the Social Theatre, edited by William Kozlenko. New York: Random House One-act play written with Paul Field Sifton, Kate Larsen, published in the One Act Play Magazine (June-July 1938)
1939 One-act play written with Paul Field Sifton, The Doctors, produced in Boston, Mass., and Baltimore, Md. theaters
1939 1942 Freelance writer, Washington, D.C.
1940 One-act play, Ernie, published in the One Act Play Magazine and Theatre Review (January 1940)
1943 1945 Coeditor with Paul Field Sifton of the U.D.A.Congressional Newsletter, for the Union for Democratic Action
1946 1948 Editorial consultant for the National Education Association and for the U.S. Children's Bureau
1949 1962 Freelance writer, Washington, D.C.
1980, Feb. 9 Died, Oaxaca, Mexico
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Paul Field Sifton (1897-1972) and Claire Ginsburg Sifton (1897-1980) span the years 1912-1980, but cover primarily the period 1925-1971. They consist of correspondence, diaries, subject files, writings, personal files, printed matter, and miscellany. The collection is of interest to students of twentieth-century American social theater, of the emergence of various labor organizations as a growing political force, and of the methodology of legislative lobbying on Capitol Hill in behalf of farmers, labor, civil rights, full employment, and other social causes. The papers are organized into nine series: Correspondence, Diaries of Claire Sifton, Subject File of Paul Field Sifton, Writings File, Personal Files, Printed Matter, Miscellany, Addition, and Oversize. Files or folders pertaining to Paul Field Sifton are connoted in the container list with the acronym PFS; those of Claire Ginsburg Sifton with the acronym CGS.
The student of the social theater will find a large number of plays in many stages of composition and production for the 1922-1950 period. The Writings File includes material on the press reaction and controversy which surrounded many of the Siftons' plays: The Belt (1927), an indictment of Henry Ford's "speedup" system, was attacked as anti-capitalist. Midnight (1930), which was against capital punishment and press sensationalism, was criticized on both counts. 1931--- (1931), a naturalistic vision of unemployment and the Great Depression, was both praised and attacked from several points of view. Blood on the Moon (1933), a strong, early condemnation of Nazi Germany, was both eulogized and vilified; its London production was halted by the Lord Chamberlain as insulting to a foreign power. The one-act play, The Doctors (1938), was roundly condemned by the American Medical Association as "sanctioning" unethical medical conduct. And The Girdle of Venus (1948-1950), depicting the role of Paul Reynaud and his mistress, Hélène comtesse de Portes, in the fall of France, was dropped by the Theatre Guild when the countess's living children threatened libel action. Additionally, the Writings File includes poetry of Paul Sifton as well as short stories, book reviews, and newspapers and magazine articles of Paul and Claire Sifton. Several disparate book projects, 1922-1962, of Paul Sifton complete the Writings File.
Of importance to the students of the politics of labor organization and of the methodology of Washington lobbying are the Subject File of Paul Sifton. His involvement in the nation's first full-fledged unemployment compensation system (New York State, 1934-1938) led to his post in the newly created Wages and Hours Division in the Department of Labor. This was followed by his position as consumers' counsel, Bituminous Coal Administration, Department of the Interior. After leaving government service in 1941, he became national legislative representative for a number of organizations including the National Farmers' Union, the Union for Democratic Action, and the National Council for a Permanent Fair Employment Practice Committee, among others. Additionally, during World War II, he served as a labor representative on the War Manpower Commission. From 1948 until his retirement in 1962, Paul Sifton devoted his time and attention to the position of national legislative representative of the International Union, United Automobile Workers of America (CIO). The subject files have some chronological overlapping, particularly in the 1941-1947 period when he engaged in successive lobbying efforts in behalf of several complementary causes.
The Correspondence series, Diaries of Claire Sifton, material on a 1963 testimonial dinner to Paul Sifton, and the Miscellany reflect the couple's involvement in writing and the theater as well as their interest in farmers, labor, women, civil rights, full employment, and other contemporary issues.
The largest amount of personal correspondence occurred in the summers when Claire Sifton went to Maine with her two sons, and Paul remained in New York City and (later) Washington, D.C. Theatrical and literary correspondence is concentrated in the 1929-1940 period. After 1941, the non-family correspondence touches on many of the topics covered in the Subject File of Paul Sifton. The Diaries of Claire Sifton include detailed comment on college life in the 1915-1916 period; the thoughts of a young working woman in Manhattan in 1922; the private comments of a government official's wife in late New Deal Washington; and some increasingly philosophical and introspective observations in her later years. Perhaps the most interesting contemporary evaluations of Paul Sifton's impact and influence on others are contained in the letters presented to him at the testimonial dinner in his honor in 1963.
The Printed Matter series includes material Paul Sifton retained for an eventual evaluation of his work and career. The Miscellany documents a new group of interests that engaged his attention in the last decade of his life. A victim of emphysema, he felt that pollution abatement, alternative energy systems, use of non-fossil fuels, and the use of fish protein (for the underdeveloped areas of the world) were of paramount importance to mankind's survival on the planet. The last segment of the Miscellany comprises obituary, funeral, and condolence material on the Siftons, as well as photographs, press cards, address files, family genealogy, and other items.
Eminent figures represented in the letters presented at the testimonial dinner to Paul Sifton in 1963 include John F. Kennedy and past and incumbent senators, congressmen, cabinet officers, and numerous officials in farmer, labor, political, governmental, and social welfare organizations. Other prominent correspondents in the collection include Esther Root Adams (Mrs. "F.P.A."), Brooks Atkinson, Helen Gahagan Douglas, Paul H. Douglas, attorney Walter Frank, British freelance writer Ruth Esther Howe, German-language translator Heinrich Kranz, James I. Loeb, writer David Loth, Norma Millay, theatrical agent Adrienne Morrison, Reinhold Niebuhr, National Farmers' Union president James G. Patton, Roy Reuther, Victor Reuther, and Walter Reuther, New Yorker cartoonist Carl Rose, theatrical agent Leah Javne Salisbury, producer Herman Shumlin, and publisher Herbert Bayard Swope.
On Claire Sifton's background and childhood as the daughter of Southern Baptist missionaries to Brazil, the reader is referred to her father's official work, A Wandering Jew in Brazil: An Autobiography of Solomon L. Ginsburg (Nashville, Southern Baptist Convention, 1922), and to her sister's more lighthearted work, Henriqueta Chamberlain, Where the Sabia Sings: A Partial Autobiography (New York, Macmillan, 1947). On Paul Sifton's Canadian family background, see the near-print genealogies as well as two issues of Maclean's magazine, December 5 and 19, 1959, that depict the Canadian branch of the family.
Arrangement of the Papers
The collection is arranged in nine series:
Correspondence, 1917-1972
Diaries of Claire Sifton, 1912-1978
Subject File of Paul Field Sifton, 1934-1971
Writings File, 1922-1968
Personal Files, 1963
Printed Matter, 1919-1971
Miscellany, 1920s-1980
Addition, 1923-1948
Oversize, 1929-1942
Container List
- Correspondence, 1917-1972 (Box 1-7)
  In addition to personal and family correspondence, this group includes material on theatrical and literary works (including acceptance, rejection, press reaction, and censorship); job security and the writer's market in the Great Depression; the effects of working inside and outside the federal government service in Washington, D.C.; and disparate lobbying activities that engaged Paul and Claire Sifton.
  Arranged chronologically. Undated material is placed at the end of each decade.
  - 1917 (Box 1)
  - 1923-1929, (2 folders)
  - 1920s, New York
  - 1930, (2 folders)
  - 1931-1934, (4 folders) (Box 2)
  - 1935-1937, (4 folders) (Box 3)
  - 1938-1939, (2 folders) (Box 4)
  - 1930s, New York
  - 1940-1949, (7 folders) (Box 5)
  - 1940s, New York
  - 1950-1957, (8 folders) (Box 6)
  - 1957, on deaths of Mary Taylor and of Donald Montgomery
  - 1958-1959, (2 folders)
  - 1950s, New York
  - 1960-1962, (3 folders)
  - 1963-1968, (6 folders) (Box 7)
  - 1968, on the death of Estella M. Strayer
  - 1969
  - 1960s
  - 1970-1972, (2 folders)
- Diaries of Claire Sifton, 1912-1978 (Box 8-11)
  Personal diaries and ledger/account books kept by Claire Sifton.
  Arranged chronologically.
  - 1912-1913, Hyde Park School, Kansas City, Mo. (Box 8)
  - 1915, Oct. 19-Nov. 15, Stephens College, Columbia, Mo.
  - 1915, Nov. 15-1916, Jan. 3, Stephens College, Columbia, Mo.
  - 1916, Jan. 4-Feb. 26, Stephens College, Columbia, Mo.
  - 1916, Feb. 28-May 8, Stephens College, Columbia, Mo.
  - 1922, Manhattan, New York
  - 1924, by Paul Sifton, an evaluation of 1924
  - 1926-1928, expenses, (2 vols.)
  - 1931-1938, ledgers and accounts, Manhattan, N.Y. (Box 9)
  - 1934, summer trip to Mesabi Iron Range, Minnesota, notes
  - 1935-1939, New York City, N.Y.
  - 1938, Oct. 6-1939, Oct. 17, Washington, D.C.
  - 1939, Nov. 13-1942, Mar. 30, Washington, D.C. (Box 10)
  - 1949, May 28-Sept. 9, Washington, D.C.
  - 1960, July 2-Nov. 1, Maine and Washington, D.C.
  - 1963, Jamaica, Washington, D.C., and Maine (Box 11)
  - 1964, Jamaica, Delaware, Washington, D.C., and Maine
  - 1972, Maine and Mexico, fragments
  - 1973, Oct. 15-1974, Sept. 29, Maine, Washington, D.C., and Mexico
  - 1974, Oct. 2-1975, May 6, Washington, D.C. and Mexico
  - 1975, May 8-Sept. 27, Washington, D.C., and Maine
  - 1975, Sept. 26-1976, Nov. 12, Maine, Washington, D.C., and Mexico
  - 1976, Nov. 23-1978, Oct. 10, Maine, Washington, D.C., and Mexico
- Subject File of Paul Field Sifton, 1934-1971 (Box 12-37)
  Printed matter and a wide variety of miscellaneous material. This group closely follows the career changes in Paul Sifton's life. The last container in the series comprises personnel, loyalty, and medical files on Paul Sifton and a personnel file on Claire Sifton.
  Organized chronologically within each subject; undated material as well as print and near-print items follow the dated items in each group.
  - New York State Department of Labor, 1934-1939, (6 folders) (Box 12)
  - United States Department of Labor (Box 13)
    - 1930s, background for wages and hours bills
    - 1938-1939, (3 folders)
  - United States Department of the Interior (Box 14)
    - Consumers' counsel, Bituminous Coal Administration, 1939-1941, (5 folders)
    - Miscellaneous print and near-print material (Box 15)
  - Wartime mobilization See also Containers 19-20, same heading (Box 16)
    - 1940-1942, (4 folders)
    - 1943, mobilization items (Box 17)
    - 1944, wartime mobilization
    - 1945, mobilization items
  - Peacetime reconversion
    - 1945, war and peace
    - 1945, war and peace items (general)
    - 1946 (Jan.-June), war and peace (Box 18)
    - 1946 (July-Dec.), peacetime reconversion
    - 1946, peacetime items (general)
    - Fragments
  - Wartime mobilization See also Containers 16-17, same heading (Box 19)
    - Worksheets on wartime production
    - Newspaper clippings
    - Print and near-print material (Box 20)
  - National Farmers' Union (Box 21)
    - 1941-1942
    - 1943
    - 1944
    - 1945 (Box 22)
    - 1946
    - 1948-1962
    - Fragments and miscellany
    - Proposed Missouri Valley Authority legislation, (2 folders) (Box 23)
    - Print and near-print material
  - Union for Democratic Action (Box 24)
    - 1943
    - 1944, (2 folders)
    - 1945 (Box 25)
    - 1945, full employment bill
  - U.D.A. Congressional Newsletter, edited by the Siftons
    - Fragments
    - Print and near-print material (Box 26)
  - Lobbying (various) (Box 27)
    - 1940, fight against the poll tax
    - 1944
    - 1945
    - 1946, (2 folders)
    - 1947 (Box 28)
    - 1948-1962
    - Miscellany
  - UAW-CIO (Box 29)
    - Pre-1945, background of General Motors strike
    - 1945-1947, (3 folders)
    - 1948-1951, (4 folders) (Box 30)
    - 1951, PFS testimony before Senate committee
    - 1952
    - 1952, PFS testimony before Senate committee
    - 1953-1957, (5 folders)
    - 1958 (Box 31)
    - 1958, Joe Kamp case
    - 1959-1960, (2 folders)
    - 1961 (Box 32)
      - Jan.-June, (3 folders)
      - July-Dec., (3 folders) (Box 33)
    - 1962
      - Jan.-June
      - July-Dec., (2 folders) (Box 34)
    - 1963-1964, (3 folders)
    - Miscellaneous office files (Box 35)
    - 1965-1971, (8 folders) (Box 36)
  - Personnel, loyalty, and medical files (Box 37)
    - 1929-1947, personnel files [PFS], (2 folders)
    - 1913-1947, personnel files [PFS and CGS]; obituaries
    - 1929-1964, Veterans Administration files [PFS]